Inventory of the Said Hyder Akbar Sound Recordings
Hoover Institution Archives
Said Hyder Akbar sound recordings
2002-2003
2008C35
Akbar, Said Hyder, collector
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet) (17 cassettes and 25 MiniDiscs)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Sound recordings relating to conditions in Afghanistan.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
These sound recordings, which relate to conditions in Afghanistan, were created by Akbar during his trips to Afghanistan. The cassettes were generated from his first trip in summer 2002, and the MindiDiscs came from his following trip, in 2003. The recordings of both trips were the basis for successive radio documentaries on Ira Glass's "This American Life" (Chicago Public Radio).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Afghanistan--History--2001-; Phonotapes.
Collection Contents
- Sound recordings of Afghanistan trip, 2002 May-September (Box 1)
  17 audio cassette tapes
  - Sound recording of commentary in anticipation of Akbar's trip to Afghanistan, 2002 May 4; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002959 (Box 1)
    In preparation for a trip to Afghanistan, Akbar comments on what he hopes to take in. Though he is only going for a couple months, he believes he will delay his return home once he's in Afghanistan. He is in awe of his father's new, high-profile position, and he believes his father will shortly become the governor of the Kunar province. He then contemplates the realities of a region at war, including the bombing of Kunar and casualties his family knows. This prompts him to look for news online. Following, he contemplates things he needs to do before he leaves including refreshing his skills with an Afghan alphabet and figuring out when he gets his high school diploma. In English
  - Narration describing Afghanistan in Spring 2002, 2002 May - June; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002770 (Box 1)
    Akbar narrates his travels from Pakistan, through the Khyber Pass, and into Jalalabad and Kabul. He describes various aspects of the area, including, but not limited to, the chaotic driving environment, post-conflict devastation, marketplaces, the reaction of locals to seeing someone with a microphone, interactions with family and important family friends, the hotel in Kabul, and his personal trip from San Francisco to Afghanistan. Throughout, Akbar is interested in recording ambient noises. The sound quality is good, but there is significant background noise throughout. Though Akbar narrates in English, he often interacts with locals in the native language. Label reads: Tape #1 Peshawar - Kabul. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in Spring 2002, 2002 June; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002771 (Box 1)
    Side B describes Akbar's family friends before recounting the trip from Pakistan to Afghanistan through the Khyber Pass. He goes on to detail spending time with his father and introduction to Afghan politics. Side A label reads: Hyder Tape #2 Commentary. Side B label reads: Hyder Tape #2 Personal Comm. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in June 2002, 2002 June; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002772 (Box 1)
    In this recording Akbar describes meeting important people in Afghan politics--ministers, warlords, Karzai, etc. Akbar also describes how one passes time without television, radio, or Internet. Includes commentary about the Loya jirga. Side A and B labels both read: Hyder Tape #3. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in June 2002, 2002 June; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002773 (Box 1)
    Commentary topics on this recording include the results of Loya Jirga, the funeral of Akbar's great-grandfather, and why his grandfather turned down the chance to be head-of-state. Side B label reads: Tape #4 Baba Going to Kunar. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in July 2002, 2002 July 6; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002817 (Box 1)
    This commentary follows an assassination of a family friend and minister. Akbar describes the first days of his father's role as Karzi's spokesman dealing with this event. Side A label reads: #5. Side B label reads: Assasination of Haji Jedir #5. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in July 2002, 2002 July 15; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002818 (Box 1)
    This recording describes, among other topics, Akbar's uncle with a glass eye, the Afghan experience with past wars versus the American experience with past wars, how his father grew up, American media in Afghanistan, the Afghan people and their culture. Side A label reads: Tape #6 Raox Mama. Side B label reads: Tape #6 Naab [??] Violence. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in July 2002, 2002 July; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002819 (Box 1)
    This tape describes Akbar's experiences with the American media in Afghanistan, the impact of decades of war, his frustration with Afghan political leaders, opposition to and danger to his father, and the lack of luxuries in Afghanistan. Side A label reads: Hyder Akbar Tape #7. Side B label reads: Frustration! In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in summer 2002, 2002 summer; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002820 (Box 1)
    Akbar narrates a car trip on the first side. On the second side he plays the radio and comments on the songs. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in summer 2002, 2002 summer; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002915 (Box 1)
    Akbar describes traveling in a car in Kabul, comments on Afghan life/culture, describes getting sick on bad food, and relates why he is excited to return to America. He had recently returned from a trip to northern Afghanistan. Label reads: Hyder Tape #9. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary describing Afghanistan in September 2002, 2002 September 5-6; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002916 (Box 1)
    In this recording Akbar describes food options concerning what makes his stomach sick, a bomb explosion that shook the hotel and killed lots of people, and the assassination attempt on Karzai. Included are recordings he made of BBC coverage of the bombing and assassination attempt. He offers analysis that the Karzai government is ineffective; that neighboring countries want an unstable, war-torn Afghanistan; how the attempt will not be answered by the administration; and comparing the attempt to the start of the Jihad against the Soviets and as the start of a new movement of regrouped Taliban. Label reads: Tape #10 Assassination. In English
  - Sound recording of the press conference regarding the assassination attempt on President Karzai in 2002, 2002 September 6; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002917 (Box 1)
    Akbar sits and records in front of the BBC at the press conference. Side A label reads: Tape #11 Day at Palace. Side B label reads: Tape #11 Press Conference. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary on Afghan life in summer 2002, 2002 September 6-7; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002918 (Box 1)
    Akbar describes Karzai's office during an interview, his second to last night in Afghanistan, guns, and a ride in an old Soviet helicopter. Side A label reads: Tape #12. Side B label reads: Tape #12 Panjaher. In English
  - Sound recording from Afghanistan in September 2002, 2002 September 11; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002957 (Box 1)
    Akbar narrates his last day in Kabul, time in Jalalabad, and provides commentary on related issues. Covers the end of a press conference, a final helicopter ride, a trip to a grave, what people will do to get to America, his last dinner in Afghanistan, time spent in Peshawar, and leaving to go back to America. While Akbar's notes are in English, the dinner is in a local language. Label reads: Tape 13. In English
  - Sound recording from Pakistan in September 2002, 2002 September 11; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0002958 (Box 1)
    Final concluding notes from Akbar's trip. Label reads: #14. In English
- Sound recordings of Afghanistan trip, 2003 (Box 1)
  25 MiniDiscs. Disc 17 is corrupt and the contents is largely unintelligible.
  - Sound recording of interviews and commentary regarding Afghan politics in 2003, Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003077 (Box 1)
    This minidisc has many different recordings on it. The first is an English-language interview between a western journalist and Akbar's father. It concerns the chaos in Afghanistan, the influence of warlords, and regrouping of the Taliban. Following, Akbar describes how he needs armed guards to go out in the city. Next is a recording of one of his father's business meetings. Akbar then discusses a jirga. Please note that this minidisc has become corrupt and the final 18 minutes and 20 seconds are unavailable. Possibly minidisc 20a. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003078 (Box 1)
    Akbar discusses a variety of topics in preparation for his return to Afghanistan. It sounds like he was on the phone with someone and this is a recording of his side. First is a person mentioned before, Julalie (sp?), Interior Minister of Afghanistan. Then he discusses an ad in an anti-Pasto newspaper for a press secretary. Prior to taking out the ad, those responsible didn't inform Akbar's father, who was the press secretary. Akbar notes his father is in Kunar in order to help confront the warlords and has since been attacked. Akbar lays out what he expects in his trip. In ways this trip will be different than his first the year before; he believes he will be better prepared, and he believes he'll be much more comfortable in Kunar than trapped in a Kabul hotel. He notes how the trip relates to his studies in college. He reflects on going to a community college versus a traditional college. He says Afghanistan is full of western-trained professionals, but that's a moot point due to political/war issues. He wants to use his education to do good for Afghanistan. For example, he's thinking about majoring in economics, as opposed to his previous focus on getting an MBA. During his comments, he reflects on the fact that he doesn't dream at night like he did as a child. He mentions the relationship between Kabul and the providences. He speaks about the importance of beards in Afghanistan. Label reads: Hyder Akbar Kunar Tape # 1 "Pre-Kunar 1." In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003079 (Box 1)
    Label reads: Hyder Disc 2 "pre-kunar 2" KUNARLOG2. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003 May; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003080 (Box 1)
    Akbar records in preparation for his trip to Afghanistan. He provides an overview of his recording equipment. He describes his room. He talks about his upcoming trip, including that a helicopter will await him to take him to Kunar. He is looking forward to driving around Hong Kong during a layover. He plays the computer game Civilization 3. He then reads news about Afghanistan, including an article from the Guardian. Label reads: Hyder Disc 3 Mic Check "lav check 1" 5/03 KUNARLOG3. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003 May; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003088 (Box 1)
    Label reads: Hyder Mic Check Second Recorder 3rd Disk "lavcheck 2" 5/03. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003089 (Box 1)
    Label reads: Disc #4 Hyder Kunar 4a. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003090 (Box 1)
    Label reads: Hyder Akbar Disc 5. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003091 (Box 1)
    First day in Afghanistan/airport. Label: Disc 6. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003092 (Box 1)
    Road arrival in Kunar. Label: Disc 7. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003099 (Box 1)
    Kunar, prison, mass graves. Label: Disc 8. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003100 (Box 1)
    Personal audio, road to Karuagal, Americans. Label: Disc 9. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003101 (Box 1)
    Arrival to Karungal, talk with elders, Shara, Americans. Disc 10. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003102. In English (Box 1)
    Ambush. Disc 11
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003103 (Box 1)
    Ambush continued, border trouble, personal audio. Disc 12. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003104 (Box 1)
    Personal Audio. Disc 13. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003109 (Box 1)
    Kerala, mass graves. Disc 14. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003110 (Box 1)
    Arriving to Kabul, Personal Conn. Disc 15. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003111 (Box 1)
    Dinner with (sensitive Karzai convo), Kabul Palace. Disc 16. In English
  - Sound recordings of an interview with Khalilzad and other commentary, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0004966 (Box 1)
    This MiniDisc is corrupted. While the interview with Khalilzad is mostly unintelligible, it may be possible to figure out what is being talked about. The commentary section of this disc is okay. Disc 17. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003112 (Box 1)
    Over the border, Bajaar, Mama Tour. Disc 18. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003113 (Box 1)
    Personal Comm, Kunar Thing. Disc 19. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003424 (Box 1)
    Personal Comm., Najishu, mama, Pech Valley, Armed Guards. Disc 20. In English
  - Sound recording of an interview with Karzai, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003425 (Box 1)
    Kabul. Disc 20b. In English
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003426 (Box 1)
    Raouj Mama interview. Disc 21
  - Sound recording of commentary regarding a trip to Afghanistan, 2003; Use copy reference number: 2008c35_a_0003427 (Box 1)
    Mama interview, personal audio. Disc 22. In English